Finding aid to the Student Demonstrations collection CA.MS.00317
Smith College Archives
Student Demonstrations collection
1933-2007
Smith College Archives
Smith College.
CA.MS.00317
0.625 linear feet (2 containers)
The Student Demonstrations collection contain a wide range of information about the history of political demonstrations at Smith College.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in the Student Demonstrations collection were donated to the Smith College Archives over a period of time from a variety of sources.
Biographical / Historical
The Student Demonstrations collection document how Smith College students have expressed their opposition to national and local issues through rallies and protests since 1933. Major events such as the United States' involvement in World War II, presidential elections, and segregation prompted the majority of student demonstrations from the 1930s to 1960s. Issues of the 1980s and 1990s include opposition to the Persian Gulf War, support for Ada Comstock Scholars, as well as rallies to help improve women's safety on college campuses.
The 1986 occupation of College Hall makes up the largest portion of the Student Demonstration files. These folders contain both primary and secondary sources, documenting Smith students' opposition to the Board of Trustees' investment in South African companies that contributed to apartheid. Included in these materials is a student oral history project that features taped recordings of those who oparticipated in the occupation.
Related Materials
Researchers should also view:
- 80. College Hall Occupation Oral History Project
- 80. Student Strike 1970
Scope and Contents
The Student Demonstrations collection include documents that relate to demonstrations and protests conducted by Smith College students from 1933 to present. These activities include rallies and campaigns regarding national and local issues, ranging from opposition to U.S. wars abroad to conflicts of racism on the Smith campus. Types of materials include academic papers, news clippings, newsletters, photographs, protest signs, and student diaries.
Demonstrations
- Demonstrations, 1933-1935 (Box 3023, Folder 1)
- Demonstrations (including Riots), 1936-1937 (Box 3023, Folder 2)
- Demonstrations, 1940-1949 (Box 3023, Folder 3)
- Demonstrations (including Photos), 1950-1959 (Box 3023, Folder 4)
- Demonstrations, 1960-1965 (Box 3023, Folder 5)
- Demonstrations, 1965-1966 (Box 3023, Folder 6)
- Demonstrations, 1966-1967 (Box 3023, Folder 7)
- Demonstrations, 1967-1968 (Box 3023, Folder 8)
- Demonstrations (including News clippings), March 1967 (Box 3023, Folder 9)
- Demonstrations (including News clippings), 1967 (Box 3023, Folder 10)
- Fast For Peace, 1968 (Box 3023, Folder 11)
- Demonstrations (News clippings), 1968 (Box 3023, Folder 12)
- Demonstrations, 1968-1969 (Box 3023, Folder 13)
- Demonstrations (News clippings), 1968-1969 (Box 3023, Folder 14)
- Demonstrations (Photographs), October 1969 (Box 3023, Folder 15)
- Day of Dialogue, 1969 (Box 3023, Folder 16)
- Work for Peace, October 1969 (Box 3023, Folder 17)
- National Student Strike, 1969-1970 (Box 3023, Folder 18)
- Demonstrations, 1970-1972 (Box 3023, Folder 19)
- Demonstrations (News clippings), 1971-1972 (Box 3023, Folder 20)
- Demonstrations, 1973-1974 (Box 3023, Folder 21)
- South Africa, 1975-1980 (Box 3023, Folder 22)
- Demonstrations, 1981 (Box 3023, Folder 23)
- Demonstrations, 1986 (Box 3023, Folder 24)
- College Hall Occupation
  - "Why Smith, Why Now?" - Donna Kenny, 1986 (Box 3023, Folder 25)
  - "It Happened at Smith" - Maureen Dooley Lawrence, 1986 (Box 3023, Folder 26)
  - Diaries, 1986 (Box 3023, Folder 27)
  - Notes by Rebecca Loveland, Class of 1988, 1986 (Box 3023, Folder 28)
  - Signs, 1986 (Box 3023, Folder 29)
  - Statements of Support - Notes from Mary Maples Dunn, 1986 (Box 3023.1, Folder 1)
  - Student Proposal for Settlement, 1986 (Box 3023.1, Folder 2)
  - Lists of People at Sit-in & Supporters, 1986 (Box 3023.1, Folder 3)
  - Trustee Investment Policy Statements, 1986 (Box 3023.1, Folder 4)
  - Press Coverage and Public Relations, 1986 (Box 3023.1, Folder 5)
  - Community Policy Committee Report, October 1986 (Box 3023.1, Folder 6)
- Women's March for Life - Washington, D.C., 1986 (Box 3023.1, Folder 7)
- C.I.A. Recruiting, 1987 (Box 3023.1, Folder 8)
- Space for Multicultural Organizations, 1990 (Box 3023.1, Folder 9)
- Persian Gulf War, 1991 (Box 3023.1, Folder 10)
- United Student Employee Delegation (USED), 1991 (Box 3023.1, Folder 11)
- Rodney King Verdict, 1992 (Box 3023.1, Folder 12)
- Rally for Ada's, 1994 (Box 3023.1, Folder 13)
- Chain for Change, 1996 (Box 3023.1, Folder 14)
- Demonstrations, 1997-1998 (Box 3023.1, Folder 15)
- Demonstrations, 1999 (Box 3023.1, Folder 16)
- Blackface Incident (Posters, etc.), 2007 (Box 3023.1, Folder 17)
- Occupation of College Hall Oral History Project, 1986
  General
  There are none audio tapes, #s 168-176, of interviews in the AV collection. This material has also been digitized. Papers related to this student project are in container 3023.1.